Whitman College Employees Association Records 1967, 1975-1986
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
Whitman College Employees Association Records
1967, 1975-1986
Whitman College and Northwest Archives 345 Boyer Avenue Walla Walla, WA 99362 Archives@whitman.edu https://library.whitman.edu/archives/
Whitman College. Whitman College Employees Association
WCA.158
0.8 linear feet 2 manuscript boxes
The Whitman College Employees Association (WCEA) was formed in 1978 to promote better working conditions and secure transparent policies for non-faculty staff. The Whitman College Employees Association Records, which date from 1975 to 1986, consist of newsletters, correspondence, memoranda, survey data, and information about organized labor, evidencing the activities of the WCEA.
Materials related to personnel, grievances, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are restricted for 75 years.
This collection has been arranged by an archivist. The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The Whitman College Employees Association (WCEA) was formed on January 25, 1978 by a nearly unanimous vote of forty seven college staff members. According to the WCEA constitution and bylaws, the purpose of the organization was to "promote the welfare of the employees of Whitman College and to secure a better means of communication with the administration of the College." The formation of WCEA began in 1977 when Whitman staff members Claire Norsworthy, Sandi Jensen, Sharon Kespohl, Sally Weakley, Donna Chiarelott, Mike Soper, and Carol Paynter, distributed a questionnaire to women staff members employed by the college. The questionnaire included questions about salary, job classification, opportunities for promotion, and workplace satisfaction. A majority of the responses indicated dissatisfaction with working conditions at Whitman, including unfair salary practices, no written set of regulations or policies, and informal job descriptions. Over the next several years, the WCEA was able to negotiate a slight increase in staff salaries, the publication of a staff handbook which included information about fringe benefits and job categorization, and a formal grievance policy. The association also organized several additional salary surveys, worked to educate staff about their rights as employees, and continued to push for pay equity. According to the records, the WCEA appears to have no longer been active after 1987 due to low membership, but at its height more than fifty percent of staff were involved.
The Whitman College Employees Association (WCEA) Records houses the organizational records of the WCEA. This collection, which dates from 1975 to 1987, consist of newsletters, correspondence, memoranda, survey data, and information about organized labor, evidencing the activities of the WCEA. This collection provides insight into the working conditions of Whitman College employees during the 1970s and 1980s.
Whitman College
Labor laws and legislation; Employee fringe benefits
- "Association News" Newsletter, 1978-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Budget Expenditures, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Constitution and Bylaws, 1978, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and Memoranda, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- Dues Receipt Book, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Employment Terminology and Benefit Information, 1979 March (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Fringe Benefits Committee, 1977, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- General Newspaper Clippings, Articles, and Resources about Labor and Employee Rights, 1973-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
- Grievance Committee Memoranda, 1978 May (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Grievance Committee Policies and Procedures, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Individual Retirement Account Documentation, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Job Classification Committee, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Job Satisfaction Questionnaire, 1977-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Local Newspaper Clippings about Whitman Employees Association, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Meeting Announcements, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Meeting Minutes, 1978-1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Membership Rolls, 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- New Employee Enrollment Packet From Controller's Office, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Return of Organization Exempt from Income Tax, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Salary Survey, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
- Staff Grievances, 1978 April-May, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  RESTRICTED UNITL 2056
- Staff Handbook Revisions, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- "Under-The-Tower-Talk" Newsletters, 1981-1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Whitman College and the Fair Labor Standards Act, 1967 October (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Whitman College Payroll/Personnel System, 1979 March 03 (Box 2, Folder 19)